Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Okay, so today's דף daf *daf* is
נ"ו *Nun Vav* and we pick up in the middle of נ"ה
עמוד ב' *Nun Hey amud bet*, and the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* was trying to figure out why רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi
Yehuda* didn't need it there to be only one, only one pedestal,
why he couldn't have the two pedestals? So the first suggestion was
that he didn't trust that writing would do the job, that he
felt that writing would, that people don't pay attention to writing and
wanted to base it on his position about having, not having separate
שופרות *shofrot*, essentially צדקה *tzedakah* boxes or whatever, contribution boxes, in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* for the, for the birds that
are חובה *chova*, obligatory, which are divided between חטאת chatas. *chatas* and
עולה olah *olah*, and those that are pure נדבה *nidavah* which are
all עולה *olah*. And the concern was mixtures. So what's the concern
of mixtures? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said the concern is is
that you won't pay attention to what's written on which one and
you'll put the, you know, money that goes into one into the
other. And that shows that he doesn't rely on writing and that's
the same issue about the pedestals. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
that doesn't make sense because obviously he relies on writing because there
were thirteen שופרות *shofrot*
and therefore you had to know how each one was different from
every other one and quoted a ברייתא *Baraita*, a משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*,
excuse me, that said what was written on each one and had
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* as one of the speakers of
that משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, so clearly רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
relies on writing and you could pay attention to the writing. So
we have to now figure out two things as left to figure
out. Number one, איכא *ika*, what's the concern about about having the
שופר *shofar* for the obligatory birds and that to the free will,
what's the concern of the mixtures? And the other issue is why
doesn't he have two pedestals on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*,
why does he only have one? We tried to connect those but
now we're seeing that those are not connected ideas. So we pick
up on the middle of נ"ה עמוד ב' *Nun Hey amud bet*,
and it says the following: כי אתא רב דימי אמר Amar *Ki
ata Rav Dimi amar*. So it is ten lines from the bottom,
line starting with word אמר *amar*. When רב דימי *Rav Dimi* came
he said, כי אתא רב דימי אמר *Ki ata Rav Dimi amar*,
when רב דימי *Rav Dimi* came he said, עמי
במערבא *Amri beMa'arava*, they say in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, גזירה משום
חטאת chatas. שמתו בעליה *Gezeira mishum chatas shemesu ba'aleha*.
The concern is because of a חטאת chatas *chatas* that the owner
has died. So it's not a concern of mixing the the obligatory
money with the free will money. No, forget the free will money.
You don't want to have a, the basic point is, you don't
want somebody bringing an obligatory sacrifice or more specifically a חטאת chatas.
*chatas* unless they're bringing it in person. But for somebody to just
contribute the money and walk away and use that money for a
חטאת *chatas*, there's a concern. The concern is is that by the
time you get around to bringing that money, even if it's on
the same day, the person might have died. And then you're bringing
a חטאת *chatas* for an owner that died and that's an invalid
קרבן korban. *korban*. So the mixture is not it'll be mixed with
something else, but mixed amongst all of this money that has been
given for a חטאת *chatas*, of a, half חטאת *chatas*, half עולה
*olah*, some of it might be from somebody who died and therefore
you need the person to be bringing it in person. That's his
concern. Okay,
ומי חיישינן *Umi chaishinan*,
are we really concerned about this? ומי חיישינן *Umi chaishinan*,
I just lost my place, והתנן *ve-hatnan*, we taught in a משנה
Mishnah, *Mishnah*, השולח חטאתו ממדינת הים *Hasholeach chattato mimedinat hayam*. If that's
true that you always have to be in person, we don't want
you to just give money and then walk away because who knows
maybe the guy will have died? So then how can ever even,
how can somebody ever send it through a, you know, through an
intermediary? Somebody who sends his חטאת *chatas* from overseas, he doesn't live
in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, מקריבין אותו בחזקת שהוא קיים *makrivin oto
be-chezkat she-hu kayam*, you can bring it on the assumption the guy
is still alive. So there you go, it's exactly this case, you
don't have the guy doesn't have to be there in person. So
how is it different sending your חטאת *chatas* from overseas and putting
money and walking away? So and presumably רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* doesn't disagree with that. So why would this be any different?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא Ela *ela*, fine. It's not
because of maybe the owner died, אלא משום חטאת שמתו בעליה ודאי
vadai *ela mishum chatas shemesu ba'aleha vadai*. No, it's that the owner
definitely died and now it explains the word תערובות *ta'arovas*, mixture, meaning,
okay, normally every day you can bring it in and you can
assume anybody that put the money in is still alive. That by
the way is a general הלכה halacha *halacha* principle of חזקה *chazaka*.
If you were alive when you put the money in, we're going
to assume that you maintain that status quo and the guy is
still alive now. Okay, we don't assume that that status changed. But
what happens if people put in the money and then word comes
to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* while they're using the money, oh
by the way we just heard one of the guys that contributed
the money today, put money in the box today, he died today.
Okay, so now what are they going to do? Now they know
for sure that in that money is, in the money that's in
that box, is some of that money is money from a person
who died. Some of that money can't be used. But how do
they distinguish which money is which? How do they figure out, oh
this is the twenty dollars that the guy who died did, let's
take that twenty dollars out. They don't know which is the twenty
dollars that was given by the guy who died, they know a
guy definitely died, so they know in here is... is money that
can't be used, but it's all mixed up. So because we are
concerned of the scenario that there will happen to be a case
that one guy, that a guy will die and then we won't
be able to use the money for that day, we'll have to
throw all the money out. They didn't want to do this process
ever. They never wanted to have the process of putting the money
and walk away because every now and then it'll happen that we'll
know that some of that money won't be usable and then we'll
have a problem. Okay, and that's different than obviously sending the קרבן
korban, from afar. Then there's no money, it's not mixed up with
anybody else's קרבן. Okay, so that seems like a reasonable answer. So
the גמרא Gemara says, "One minute, we have a solution. What's the
solution?" So the גמרא Gemara says,
"ונברור ארבעה זוזי." V'nivror arba'a zuzei. Why specifically four זוז? zuz? תוספות
Tosafos says that that's just an arbitrary number, "Take five bucks," "Take
a quarter." But רש"י Rashi says actually that four זוז zuz was
the average cost of a bird sacrifice. רש"י Rashi does a whole
little math to figure that out. But let's take some money, however
much that is, "ונשדי במיא." V'nishdi b'maya. Take that money, take out
of the money in the box, take four זוז, zuz, however much
is equal to a normal amount given for a קרבן, throw it
in the ocean. "והנך משתרין" V'hanach mishtarin and let the rest be
permissible. So meaning, the גמרא Gemara wants to suggest something which I
would call magic, which would be...
basically, okay, you got four זוז zuz mixed up and you don't
know which is which? Just grab some random four זוז zuz and
assume that those were the ones that had to be from the
dead guy. Okay, if we would have תערובת ta'aroves work that way,
if we'd have כשרות kashrus work that way, it'd be great. Ever
have a problem, got some טריפות treifus mixed up? Just take a
spoonful out and you'll assume that's the טריפה treif product. Okay, so
it's a very funny suggestion. Now it could be that the גמרא
gemara is willing to suggest it because basically the money would normally
be בטל ברוב, batel b'rov, right? Maybe there's an assumption that normally
the rules of ביטול bitul would apply, but maybe for certain stringencies
we don't want ביטול bitul to apply. Interesting question of does ביטול
bitul apply to money? Is that an idea of דבר חשוב davar
chashuv or not?
Does ביטול bitul apply when we're relating specifically to
sacrifices or השמיסו? hash-meisu? All these interesting discussions that we've discussed about
whether we should allow ביטול bitul to apply. But in principle, ביטול
bitul should apply here. So maybe the point is, okay, ביטול bitul
maybe should apply, you don't want to let it apply, so let's
do this trick and say that it all worked out. Okay, that
actually is something we do find in הלכה which is called "שאני
אומר," she-ani omer, because I can claim. So for example, it says
if you have two containers of wheat, one that contains תרומה terumah
and one that contains חולין. chulin. And you have on top of
it, two smaller boxes, one of חולין chulin and one of תרומה.
terumah. And one box falls into one container and one into the
other and you don't know which fell into what. So it says,
"Oh, you could assume the חולין chulin fell to the חולין," chulin,
שאני אומר, she-ani omer, "and that the תרומה terumah fell into the
תרומה." terumah. So the גמרא gemara says, "How can you assume that?
Maybe it's the opposite?" So it says, "Well, it's all rabbinic and
it's בטל ברוב batel b'rov anyway." So it would anyway be בטל
ברוב batel b'rov and it's only rabbinic, and maybe תרומה terumah nowadays
is only rabbinic, we can sort of allow ourselves to make these
assumptions. So every now and then when you have a ביטול bitul
case which really should be בטל batel but for various stringencies it
isn't, we allow ourselves to assume things worked out. So that could
be what the גמרא gemara is saying here. Take four זוז, zuz,
maybe ביטול bitul should work in principle. Take a random amount of
random four זוז, zuz, assume it's the one of the guy that
died, throw it away and say everything is fine. Okay, so why
is it a problem? So let's take a look. So the גמרא
gemara says like this: "רבי יהודה," Rebbi Yehuda רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
would say "לית ליה ברירה." leis lei breira. He doesn't hold of
ברירה. breira. That... now what does ברירה breira mean? ברירה breira is
not this magic שאני אומר. she-ani omer. ברירה breira is... I mean
it's a little bit of magic but not as much serious magic.
What
ברירה breira is is... let's take a look at the example of
ברירה breira and then we'll discuss how it relates or not. But
ברירה breira the basic concept is something that happens in the future
retroactively shows that it was always meant to happen like at the
beginning. Let's take a look. It's sort of a little deterministic. Let's
take a look. בראשית ברא B'reishis barah for example.
Something like that. ברירה breira and בראשית B'reishis have some similar words,
letters, but they're not the same. Okay, מנלן? minalan? So רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda doesn't hold of ברירה breira and therefore he can't just
throw out the money. So how do we know he doesn't hold
of ברירה? breira? So it says, "רבי יהודה
לית ליה ברירה מנלן?" Rabbi Yehuda leis lei breira minalan? Where do
you know he doesn't hold of ברירה? breira? "אילימא מהא דתנן," ilima
me-ha detnan, what we taught in the משנה. mishna. "הלוקח יין מבין
הכותים." haloke'ach yayin mibein hakutim. Somebody that buys wine from Samaritans. Now
Samaritans are assumed to on their own be good in terms of
תרומות ומעשרות. terumos and ma'asros. Yeah, but in terms of caring for
other people's observance, they're not מחמיר. machmir. So for themselves, if you
ate some food they were eating themselves, that would be fine. But
if you wanted to buy grain from them, you would have to
be concerned that they didn't take תרומות ומעשרות terumos and ma'asros because
they don't care about your observance. So if you buy this wine
from them and it's ערב שבת עם חשיכה, erev shabbos im chasheicha,
it's right about to get dark... Okay, it's right at בין השמשות,
bein hashmashos, right before בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, whole תוספות Tosafos discussing
exactly what the parameters are and how this is similar to another
case of buying wine from an עם הארץ am ha'aretz which has
a similar type of a discussion. So here you buy it from
the כותים, Cutim, what do you do? עומד ואומר, omeid ve-omeir, you
stand up
and
you say: שני לוגין שאני
עתיד להפריש הרי הן תרומה. shnei lugin she-ani asid le-hafrish harei hein
truma. The two לוג log that I am about to separate,
behold they will be תרומה, truma, meaning I am separating תרומה truma
now. Okay, but what am I separating? Which amount? You know, normally
when you separate, you have all this wine, you pour out a
little bit, this is תרומה. truma. You pour out ten percent, that's
מעשר. ma'aser. Other ten percent, that's מעשר שני. ma'aser sheini. You have
to measure. So here you're saying, okay, you know what, I'm going
to give two percent for תרומה. truma. Which two percent? Whatever two
percent I designate after שבת, Shabbos, okay, that'll be the two percent
I'm referring to right now. And whatever ten percent I designate afterwards
on מוצאי שבת, Motzaei Shabbos, that'll be the מעשר ma'aser that I'm
giving right now. So right now I'm giving the מעשר. ma'aser. You
don't know which wine it is. Is it this part of the
wine, that part, top of the barrel, bottom of the barrel? It'll
be the wine that I designate after שבת. Shabbos. Now, why aren't
I afraid that as I drink the wine on שבת, Shabbos, I'm
going to drink... I'm going to drink what I made? No, because
whatever I drink won't be the stuff that I designate. Whatever's left
over after שבת Shabbos will be the amount... will be what I
am calling תרומות ומעשרות trumas u-ma'asros now. The stuff that I drink
won't be the stuff. The stuff that's left over and that I
designate afterwards, that'll be right now what I am making into תרומות
ומעשרות. trumas u-ma'asros. Okay? So שני לוגין שאני עתיד להפריש הרי הן
תרומה. shnei lugin she-ani asid le-hafrish harei hein truma. Two... if you
have 102, it's actually easier to assume 102, the math works out.
So if there's 102 לוג log of wine, the two לוג log
that I'll separate after שבת Shabbos will be what I'm right now
making תרומה. truma. Will be those units that I separate after שבת.
Shabbos. עשרה מעשר ראשון, asara ma'aser rishon, the next ten that I
designate after שבת Shabbos will be the ten right now that I
am separating for first מעשר. ma'aser. And then you're left with ninety.
So ten percent of the remaining ninety is nine. תשעה מעשר שני.
tisha ma'aser sheini. The remaining nine that I designate after שבת, Shabbos,
those are the nine that right now I am making into מעשר
שני. ma'aser sheini. ומיחל ושותה מיד, u-meichal ve-shoseh mi-yad, and you are
מיחל meichal and drink right away. What does מיחל meichal mean? There's
a debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafos.
רש"י Rashi says it means מחלל, mechaleil, you transfer the money of
the מעשר שני ma'aser sheini from the קדושה kedusha of the wine
to money. Although what difference does it make? You're not eating it
right now anyway, and you're going to deal with the מעשר שני
ma'aser sheini later. But רש"י Rashi is you do whatever you can
do to fix it, you know, to fix it as much as
possible. Okay? And that... so that's what רש"י Rashi says.
מחלל mechaleil on a coin. Then what do you do with this
coin?
Then later you bring the coin to ירושלים Yerushalayim and you use
it as מעשר שני. ma'aser sheini. It's מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money.
But you already did תשעה מעשר שני. tisha ma'aser sheini.
I know, so... רש"י, Rashi, there's no need to really do that.
It's just normally what you would do to fix things up is
you don't leave your מעשר שני ma'aser sheini around, you transfer it
to money, so you transfer it now. תוספות Tosafos doesn't understand the
point. You're not allowed to drink those nine units anyway. You need
them to be left over after שבת Shabbos so that they can
be defined as the nine units of the מעשר שני. ma'aser sheini.
So what difference does it make to redeem it right now? So
תוספות Tosafos says מיחל meichal just means מתחיל. matchil. מתחיל ושותה מיד,
matchil ve-shoseh mi-yad, that you right away go ahead and you can
drink it immediately.
Oh, but then it's... okay, anyway.
תוספות Tosafos doesn't say that. But anyway, okay, but that's the point,
so that's how you do it. One of these huge תוספותים Tosafosim
here is by the way to figure out that's a very similar
משנה that talks about buying wine ערב שבת Erev Shabbos from an
עם הארץ am ha'aretz and also using ברירה, breira, but there's slight
differences in how it's framed. And this for תוספות Tosafos works out
the exact nuances of all the differences between how you would handle
the scenario by an עם הארץ am ha'aretz and how by a
כותי. Kuti. The basic difference is, is that by an עם הארץ,
am ha'aretz, A: you don't need to take תרומה, truma, you assume
the עם הארץ am ha'aretz took תרומה. truma. Here it starts with
תרומה. truma. And B: that the עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, it's a
ספק safek if they took תרומות ומעשרות. trumas u-ma'asros. By the כותי,
Kuti, you assume it's a ודאי that they did not. And because
it's a ספק, safek, we give you more latitude by an עם
הארץ, am ha'aretz, we even let you do this בין השמשות, bein
hashmashos, whereas by the כותי, Kuti, we only allow you to do
this on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos before it becomes בין השמשות. bein
hashmashos.
So even if it means before...
yeah, yeah, yes, that's how תוספות Tosafos understands it.
Yes. Because it's really מבעוד יום.
m'be'od yom. Yeah, exactly. Okay, so now, anyway, this is the difference.
דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
said. So this by the way is the principle of ברירה. breira.
Because right now I am saying I am doing this right now
on which object? The object to be named later. That's the object
that I am referring to right now. And then when I name
it later, we retroactively say that was the object you were referring
to on Friday afternoon. רבי יהודה, רבי יוסי, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Yehuda,
Rabbi Yosei, Rabbi Shimon, now on נ"ו עמוד ב', nun-vav amud beis,
רבי יהודה, רבי יוסי, ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi Yosei, and Rabbi
Shimon say אוסרין, osrin, they forbid it. Now why do they forbid
it? אלמא, alma, it must be their position is
אין ברירה, ein breira, that
they don't... So they don't hold ברירה, breira, so if they don't
hold ברירה, breira, they shouldn't be able to hold of throwing the
four coins, the four זוז zuz away and saying that that was
the money that was meant for the חטאת.
Now here
is, one minute, yeah I know, here is important to though to
notice the difference between what this is and what why it's not
exactly ברירה breira with the case of the four coins. If I
would have said I am designating, you know, some of this money
as הקדש hekdesh and some of this money is חולין, chulin, and
the money that's חולין chulin is the money that I will later
take and throw out, that's חולין chulin and the rest is הקדש.
hekdesh. That's ברירה. breira. Right now I'm designating something defined based on
what's going to happen later. That was not the case by the
four זוז. zuz. By the four זוז zuz there was actually a
concrete amount of money that actually was owned by the guy who
died and he gave it as חטאת. Right, the fact that later
you pick out four זוז zuz doesn't mean that retroactively that was
the money that the guy gave. Right, as I said, that's magic.
That just means like okay, I'm going to assume it all was
exactly the way I wanted it to be. ברירה breira is that
when what happened is it retroactively can define something that was undefined
before, and it was undefined before in reference to what was going
to happen later. Then you could say based on what happens later,
it becomes retroactively defined because previously it was undefined. Now even in
there there are two scenarios. Look, a lot of these huge תוספותים,
tosfosim, what makes the דף Daf, so short today, is that there's
a lot of different סוגיות sugyot about ברירה. breira. And they all
have nuance differences and to exactly make them line up and to
figure out like does רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir according to this hold
like ברירה? breira? But if you look at a lot of other
סוגיות sugyot it seems like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir does not hold
of ברירה breira and he tries to figure out exactly which scenarios
fit in and which ones don't fit in and that's why you
have that huge תוספות, tosfos, right? So all of these have nuance
differences. But here are two cases of ברירה breira which are different
but they're still not our case of the four זוז. zuz. One
is this: you right now define something in reference to what's going
to happen later. It's undefined now but it explicitly has been labeled,
its identity determined on what's going to happen later. When it happens
later can you say retroactively it defines what has happened now? There's
another case which is which is even a bigger חידוש, chiddush, which
is two brothers inherit an estate. Okay, is everybody with me here?
Two brothers inherit an estate. Okay, and a month later they divide
the estate. Okay, and and one guy gets you know I get
this half of the of the of the house and you get
that half or you know I get these sheep and you get
those sheep. Do we say that means that retroactively in the last
month those sheep were always mine? The ones that I took at
the end of the month. Okay, that those sheep were always mine.
Or do I mean no in that last month it was owned
by the estate as an as a corporate entity it was not
retroactively mine. Now there you never said at the beginning the you
know the dead father never said oh the sheep that will be
yours will be the ones that you guys will figure out a
month later. No, it just was this estate. But the nature of
an estate is that it is something that is going to be
divided and therefore and it is indeterminate right now whose is whose
and it will eventually be decided. So there you could say although
nobody designated something now, maybe still since its whole nature is to
be divided and right now it is indeterminate whose is whose, once
it gets determined later that will retroactively define who's always but even
retroactively who's you know which sheep belong to which person. Maybe you
could say that. Although that's a bigger חידוש chiddush than when you
explicitly label it and say I am designating the stuff that later
will be defined. But both of those are in the category of
ברירה. breira. Undefined now, determined later, does what happens later retroactively give
identity and definition to what was undefined before? That is ברירה. breira.
Again, it is really completely irrelevant to the use of the גמרא
Gemara to taking four זוז zuz and throwing them in the ocean
and assuming that it's going to be the right four זוז. zuz.
Okay, it was not undefined before, it was very clearly defined before.
You're just hoping you got the right one.
Okay this is even different because we can
say
that oh okay well the reason they're not doing it isn't because
of ברירה breira it's because they're scared maybe he'll drink the whole
thing on שבת Shabbos and then he just. Okay that's what the
גמרא Gemara will say but I first wanted to just point out
that the that the comparison to ברירה breira it's important because the
most of the it says ברירה. breira. And the תוספות tosfos really
ends up to try to figure that out. It's really completely different
than ברירה. breira. All right, he doesn't have a real good answer
then but anyway but I want to just so that you have
a clear understanding of ברירה, breira, ברירה breira doesn't mean magic. What
I say now determines that that's the way it was earlier. Okay
it only works when earlier it was undefined then we can say
the future retroactively gives definition to the undefined past. Okay so anyway
let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says אלמא אין ברירה alma
ein breira so you see רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda doesn't hold of
ברירה breira and that's why he can't throw out the four זוז.
zuz. So the גמרא Gemara says ממאי mi mai how do you
know he doesn't hold of ברירה? breira? דילמא שאני התם כדקתני טעמא
dilma shani hatam kidkatani tama this is what Michael was saying maybe
he really holds like ברירה. breira. by the wine would work. So
why doesn't he let you do it? Because like it says in
the משנה, אמר לו לרבי מאיר, amar lo le-Rebbi Meir, he said
back to רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, אי אתה מודה שמא יבקע הנוד
ונמצא שותה טבלים למפריע? ee ata modeh shema yibaka hanod venimtza shoteh
tevalim lemafrea? Aren't you afraid that if you do this, maybe the
wine will spill and then there won't be any left to take?
And if there's nothing left to take, then you can't work your
whole trick that it works retroactively. It only works if there's leftover.
So Michael said you'll forget and drink it all, they said it'll
spill, but you're taking... it's very risky. You might not have leftover
by the end of שבת. Shabbat. ואמר להם, ve-amar lahem, and רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir said back to them, לכשיבקע. le-khisheyibaka. Fine. I'll worry
about it when it happens, which means I'm not worried about it.
You can worry about whether the thing will break. I'm worried the
guy doesn't have what to drink on שבת. Shabbat. I'm going to
let him do it. I'm going to assume that it'll be... that
there will be wine left over. So the גמרא Gemara says it
might be that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, holds of ברירה. breira. He's
just afraid that your... it's too risky here. אלא fine. I'll prove
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't hold of ברירה breira from the
following scenario, מדתני איא, mi-de-tani Ayo, from what איא Ayo taught. דתני
איא, de-tani Ayo, איא Ayo taught, רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer,
אין אדם מתנה על שני דברים כאחד. ein adam matneh al shnei
devarim ke-echad. A person cannot stipulate two contradictory things at once. אלא
אם בא חכם למזרח עירובו למזרח, למערב עירובו למערב. ela im ba
chacham la-mizrach eiruvo la-mizrach, la-ma'arav eiruvo la-ma'arav.
If the sage comes to the east, my עירוב eiruv will be
in the east. If the sage comes to the west, my עירוב
eiruv will be in the
west. אבל לכאן ולכאן לא, aval le-khan u-le-khan lo, but not to
say if he comes to either direction, that you can't do. What's
the scenario? So you might remember going
back to עירובין, Eiruvin, you see
there's a reason we learn these in this order. Anyway, here's the
guy, right? He lives in this district. Okay, you have 2,000 אמות
amot in every direction that you can walk outside of the city
limit. Now, you happen to know that your רבי Rebbi is coming
and he'll be staying and he will be, you know, somewhere near
your city come שבת, Shabbat, but outside of the 2,000 אמות. amot.
Okay, he'll probably be within 4,000 אמות amot of your city. Okay,
so you want to go visit him. Okay, so you're going to
make an עירוב. eiruv. Now you know if he's going to be
here, you'll make your עירוב eiruv here, which lets you go, you
know, 4,000 in this direction and you can't go at all in
the other
direction.
Right? If he's going to wind up being here, right? If he's
going to be here, then you're going to want to make your
עירוב eiruv in this direction and you won't have any way to
go in that direction. Okay. So what you normally say is: Look,
I'm not sure whether he's coming to the east or not. Let's
say the simple scenario is, you know that he might be coming
this direction, he might not. But your only concern is he's coming
to the east. So you put your עירוב eiruv here and you
say, if he's coming to the east, if he winds up coming,
then my עירוב eiruv is here. If he doesn't wind up coming,
then I just don't have an עירוב. eiruv. I'm with the city
so I get 2,000 in all the directions. Or if you think
he's coming from the west, you put your עירוב eiruv here. If
he winds up coming, then I'm going to put my עירוב eiruv
here. If not, I'm going to be with the rest of the
city. But let's say you don't know which direction he's coming, to
the east or to the west. He might be coming from either
direction. Okay, how's that even possible? Like, you know, maybe he's here,
maybe he's somewhere here so he'll sort of come in either
direction. I don't know, you'll figure it out. But anyway, you just
don't know where he's coming from, okay? So you say, you put
two עירובים, eiruvim, you put עירוב eiruv number one here and the
עירוב eiruv number two here, and you say: If he winds up
coming from the east, I'm going to go by עירוב eiruv number
one. If he winds up coming from the west, I'm going to
go by עירוב eiruv number two. If he doesn't come from the
east or the west, I'll stay at home. Okay, so you make
that stipulation. And then based on where he comes, that's where your
עירוב eiruv is. And then he comes, and that's where your עירוב
eiruv is, and that's what you're able to do. So רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda doesn't like this. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, אין אדם
מתנה על שני דברים כאחד. ein adam matneh al shnei devarim ke-echad.
You cannot stipulate about two contradictory things. אלא אם בא חכם למזרח
עירובו למזרח, למערב עירובו למערב. ela im ba chacham la-mizrach eiruvo la-mizrach,
la-ma'arav eiruvo la-ma'arav. אבל לכאן ולכאן לא. aval le-khan u-le-khan lo. But
you can't say if he comes this way or that, you know,
he comes this way to
the east, that way it's to the west. That's sort of self-contradictory.
והוינן בה, ve-havinan bah, and the גמרא Gemara says, מאי שנא לכאן
ולכאן דלא דאין ברירה, למזרח ומערב נמי אין ברירה? mai shena le-khan
u-le-khan de-lo de-ein breira, la-mizrach u-ma'arav nami ein breira? So first the
גמרא Gemara. just says that there
is... I don't get it. It's all just stipulation. If this, if
that. So if you don't like the east and the west, to
have to say stipulate both ways because אין ברירה ein breira based
on what happens later you can't say that retroactively,
excuse me,
that'll determine that's where my עירוב eiruv was. So if you don't
like the idea that based on whether he comes to the east
my עירוב eiruv is in the east, my west עירוב eiruv is
in the west, if that happens later on שבת, Shabbat, that won't
be able to retroactively determine where your עירוב eiruv was on ערב
שבת. erev Shabbat. So if you don't like that when you make
two עירובים, eiruvim, you shouldn't like it when you make only one
עירוב. eiruv. So למזרח ומערב נמי, la-mizrach u-ma'arav nami, even if you
just to the east or just to the west, why should you
allow this guy to make a stipulation? נמי אין ברירה. nami ein
breira. So you should also say how could that work? Because so
what if he shows up? You only made one possible עירוב. eiruv.
You put it in the east. If he comes to the east,
that's my עירוב. eiruv. Not I'm within my city. And then he
came to the east. Well, why should that work? That happened later
on שבת. Shabbos. How could it retroactively define what you were doing?
Says the גמרא Gemara says,
so why, what's the difference if you make only one עירוב eruv
or you make two? Either way you're stipulating and it's determined based
on what happens later.
ואמר רבי יוחנן, ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan, Rabbi Yochanan says כשכבר בא חכם.
kshe-kevar ba chacham. You're right. According to רבי יהודה, Reb Yehuda you
cannot make any עירוב eruv based on a תנאי. tenai. And there
really is no difference between making one עירוב eruv on a תנאי
tenai and two עירובים eruvs on a תנאי. tenai. So why does
he say you can make an עירוב eruv just to the east?
Because if the חכם chacham is already
distant on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos and he's only going to come
in the zone on שבת Shabbos and the condition will only be
met on שבת, Shabbos, so on שבת Shabbos the חכם chacham has
come into the zone and then my condition is met, then it
won't work. Then where my עירוב eruv is on ערב שבת Erev
Shabbos is defined by something that happens on שבת. Shabbos. But the
reality is that the חכם chacham is sitting over here. Okay.
Well, actually, no, that's your עירוב. eruv. So the reality is, so
if ערב שבת Erev Shabbos the חכם chacham was out here, it
won't work. But if on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos the חכם chacham
was already here, you just didn't know about it. Okay. So when
you place the עירוב, eruv, it wasn't going to be determined based
on what happened later. Right now the חכם chacham is already within
the zone. I might not be aware of it, but right now
he's already within the zone. So the case that רבי יהודה Reb
Yehuda says works is when you put the עירוב eruv here and
you say if the חכם chacham is already within 2,000, within 4,000
אמות amos of the city, this is my עירוב. eruv. Then that
works. Okay. Whereas, and if you put and if the case here
was you said if the חכם chacham is already within 4,000 אמות,
amos, then it works, then it's not something that happens later, then
it's right now defined. I'm ignorant of it, but right now it's
known whether the חכם chacham is there or not and whether that
is going to be an עירוב. eruv. The case that doesn't work
is if you put two עירובים eruvs here, two עירובים eruvs here
because here you can't, cause why does that not work? Because in
that scenario, although you could say he's either here or here and
I just don't know, the גמרא Gemara assumes that the scenario when
you put it to the east or the west and both and
you say it'll be defined based on what happens, but that's a
case where it hasn't happened yet.
On שבת Shabbos he's going to show up into one of those
zones.
So in the end of the day, the difference is really not
that you put two עירובים eruvs versus one עירוב. eruv. The difference
is that in one case it's already happened, so it's not based
on what's going to happen later, whereas in the other case it
is actually an issue of what is going to happen on שבת,
Shabbos, you'll turn up into one of those places and that will
define for me and that doesn't work because of ברירה. breira. So
the upshot of this is that רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda does not
allow the stipulation of the עירוב eruv to work if the if
the condition is defined it comes up on שבת. Shabbos. Because if
the condition comes up on שבת Shabbos and that's when the condition
is met and then retroactively it'll define where I made my עירוב
eruv ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, he says that I won't allow work,
that's a ברירה breira case. And from there we see that רבי
יהודה Reb Yehuda does not hold of ברירה. breira. So it doesn't
really matter one direction or two directions. What matters is, are you
saying that the condition is met before שבת? Shabbos? Then it's fine.
If the condition is met on שבת Shabbos and what happens on
שבת Shabbos retroactively determines, that is ברירה. breira. Now, one of these
big תוספותים, Tosafos-im, you know, amongst these big ones and this is
a big question by ברירה breira because mostly we say the same
that there is a big difference between ברירה breira and a תנאי.
tenai. I can sell you, you know, I can sell you here
my iPhone on the condition that, you know, that it doesn't snow
another six inches today. Okay? And then based on whether it does
or doesn't snow another six inches today, I will have sold you
my iPhone and that'll take effect as of now. Retroactively it'll take
effect as of now. It's not ברירה. breira. I am selling to
you as of now on the following condition. Okay? If anybody ever
learned מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin and מסכת קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, this is
your גט get on the condition that X. This is your קידושין
kiddushin on the condition that Y. Okay? You make a condition, when
the condition if the condition is met, retroactively it takes effect. It's
not ברירה. breira. ברירה Breira is like determining the identity of something.
It's not having a
legal act take effect based on a condition being made. You're allowed
to stipulate the conditions under which something takes effect. So why is
it different here? Why does the גמרא Gemara think that making a
condition where the חכם chacham shows up will determine where my עירוב
eruv takes effect? Why is that a ברירה? breira? That's it's not
like it's indeterminate what I'm doing defined by what happens later. No,
I've just stipulated where it'll take effect based on condition A or
condition B. So here it's
and this comes up in more than one גמרא. Gemara In more
than one גמרא Gemara it sort of identifies some things that we
would have called conditions, a תנאי, tenai, and the גמרא Gemara puts
it in the ברירה breira category.
Is the language always the same? In other words... Right, על מנת
שאני עשיר. Al menat she'ani ashir. Right.
ונמצא עני. Venimtza ani. Right.
So is that, could that language be used and then all of
a sudden the מפרשים Mefarshim will say it's a ברירה Breira question?
So it could be, right. So normally no, normally the על מנת
Al menat language is clearly תנאי, Tnai, not ברירה, Breira, and the
גמרא gemara never raises ברירה Breira by all these סוגיות Sugyot of
תנאי, Tnai, and then every now and then in a ברירה Breira
discussion it throws in some type of a condition which we would
have called the תנאי, Tnai, which we would have called a stipulation.
So the idea is to try to identify what makes that condition
different. And what I'd like to say, and I'll give you one
other example of this, I'm just allowing myself to digress for a
minute because it's such a short דף, but it is another example
and תוספות Tosafot quotes one of these cases is a man says
to a woman, it's talking about קידושי ביאה, Kidushi Biah, קידושין Kidushin
made through the act of sex, okay, which obviously we don't do,
but it's one of the theoretically ways of doing the act of
קידושין. Kidushin. Not נשואין, Nisuin, which is the way where they live
together, but the קידושין Kidushin done through sex. So the man says
to the woman, we're going to have sex, and it'll be an
act of קידושין Kidushin on the condition that your father's okay with
it. So it says רצה אב מקודשת לא רצה אינה מקודשת, Ratza
av mekudeshet lo ratza eina mekudeshet, and the גמרא gemara says that's
an issue of יש ברירה. Yesh Breira. Why is it an issue
of יש ברירה? Yesh Breira? Why isn't it an issue of a
תנאי? Tnai? We have תנאים Tnaim all the time in הלכות קידושין
Hilchot Kidushin in מסכת קידושין. Masechet Kidushin. So it seems that the
difference is the following. There is a what?
If it's something that, in other words, I say,
okay, so it could be, yeah, so
תוספות Tosafot divides, says that maybe it has a little bit to
do whether רש״י Rashi also, satisfying the condition is under your control
or not under your control. But again, it doesn't work with a
lot of the הלכות Halachot of תנאים Tnaim where it doesn't matter
whose control the condition is in, but תוספות Tosafot definitely tries to
work that angle. I think the better answer is the following: is
that there are some הלכות Halachot where the question is what are
you intending. There are others where it is whether you want your
act to take effect or not as opposed to what your intention
is, meaning,
if I say let's take a look talk about the case about
the עירוב. Eiruv. Is the עירוב Eiruv like I am doing this
act and I want it to take effect under condition A or
condition B? What's the real logic of the עירוב? Eiruv? The real
logic of the עירוב Eiruv isn't like an act of sale which
then takes effect. The real logic of the עירוב Eiruv is where
are you starting שבת? Shabbat? Where did you start שבת? Shabbat? You
started שבת, Shabbat, you started שבת Shabbat at least with the idea
of עירוב, Eiruv, where your עירוב Eiruv was, that's where you were
intending to start שבת. Shabbat. So if I ask you where do
you want to start שבת, Shabbat, did you want to start it
at home or did you want to start it two thousand אמה
Ammah out of the city? Well, where I wanted to start שבת
Shabbat depends.
If this were to happen, then I wanted to start שבת Shabbat
here, if that were to happen, I wanted to start שבת. Shabbat.
No, where you want it is a question of your current state
of mind, your current intention and your current state of mind. It's
not a question of whether an act takes effect or not. I
can do an act of קידושין Kidushin that will only take effect
under these circumstances. But if you ask me where did I want
to be, what was my intention when I was at home, did
I imagine that my home was where I was setting down for
שבת, Shabbat, did I imagine it was out there? What my state
of mind was cannot be conditional. It's a reality what my state
of mind was. The effect of my action can be conditional, but
my state of mind, I either was intending to start it here
or intending to start it there. I think the same is true
about the גמרא gemara about קידושי ביאה. Kidushi Biah. The גמרא gemara
for example of קידושי ביאה Kidushi Biah is one way to understand
that ביאה Biah is different as an act of קידושין Kidushin is,
it's a very relevant halachic question which is, if a couple is
living together as husband and wife and they never intended to do
קידושין, Kidushin, do we say that the reality of living together as
husband and wife and having sex in a marital context even without
an intention to effect קידושין, Kidushin, nevertheless that reality of that type
of marital life creates the reality of קידושין? Kidushin? There are those
that understand that that's what קידושי ביאה Kidushi Biah is. It's not
like an act which you define will take effect and the קידושין
Kidushin will be חל. Chal. Can you do קידושי ביאה לאחר זמן?
Kidushi Biah le'achar zman? We're going to have sex now and the
קידושין Kidushin will take effect in a week. You can do קידושי
כסף לאחר זמן. Kidushi kessef le'achar zman. No, the idea of קידושי
ביאה Kidushi Biah is that that reality, if you're doing it in
the context of marital sex and of a marital relationship and not
in a different type of a context, sex occurs in other contexts
as well, but if you do it in the context of marital
sex then by definition that creates the reality of קידושין. Kidushin. If
that's how you understand it, then you can't say, oh, I only
wanted it to take effect under this. What were you thinking? Were
you basically thinking seeing yourself as being married or were you basically
seeing yourself as having sex outside of marriage? You can't say, well,
it depends on what my father would have said, how I saw...
what did you, how did you basically understand what that act was?
So that's the ברירה. Breira. ברירה. Breira. means maybe it's not a
תנאי, tnai, but maybe if you believe in ברירה breira you can
even say that what was in my mind at that time can
retroactively be defined by what happens later. Okay, and that's why the
ברירה breira I think some the few times you find ברירה breira
used in a discussion of where of a תנאי tnai is that
you're not talking about an act that you are defining whether it
takes effect and under what conditions it takes effect, that's the idea
of תנאי. tnai. The question is what were you thinking at the
time? Where were you planning on starting שבת? Shabbos? How were you
thinking about this act of sex? Okay, and that you characterize how
I thought of it would be defined based on what happens later
that will retroactively define how I was thinking about it at the
time. It's not possible or it's only possible in the world of
ברירה. breira. In the world of ברירה breira you can say maybe
things that happen retroactively give definition to what was happening before.
Or only gives definition later when that thing-
yes, but when it happens then retroactively, the idea of ברירה breira
is when it happens, if you say right now my דעת daas
is
indeterminate and it'll
be defined based on later reality. Well that's exactly what ברירה breira
is. Okay. Which, which barrel of wine is תרומה truma is not
defined, it'll be defined based on what happens later. Okay. Anyway, I
just wanted to share that with you, it gives a little clarity
to both ברירה breira and to how we use the idea and
how it's different from the idea of תנאים. tnaim. Again, the גמרא
gemara here is assuming that this case of תנאי tnai is a
ברירה, breira, but for reasons I said I think it has more
to do with state of mind than with an act taking effect.
And therefore the גמרא gemara concludes that רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda does
not hold of ברירה. breira. That's why he has a problem if
the חכם chacham has not already come ערב שבת erev Shabbos for
to be determined after שבת. Shabbos. That's why he's got an issue.
And if he doesn't hold of ברירה, breira, that's why he can't
solve the problem of the mixed up money and does of the
חטאת that the owner died just throw some money out because he
doesn't hold of ברירה. breira. Of course as I told you, even
if you held of ברירה, breira, you couldn't explain how that could
work, but that's what the גמרא gemara says. Okay so now we
have said what the problem with רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda. about a
separate box for the money of these עולות, olos, of these חטאת
עולות, chatas olos, the problem is that the owner will die, there'll
be money that's mixed up that you can't use, and because he
doesn't hold of ברירה, breira, you can't take some four coins out
and just assume that those are the four coins that have to
be thrown out.
So the example of the barrels of תרומה truma would be parallel
to the couple, we'll have sex now, and if I fall in
love with you a month later then we will have been married
as of a month earlier and I guess the ביאה biah would
have been the קידושי ביאה.
kiddushei biah. Something like that. Right. That's ridiculous. Okay, so now- why
did we bring up the whole
thing of כתיבה kseiva anyway?
The reason we brought up the whole issue about the money was
we thought the reason רבי יהודה- Rabi Yehuda so thank you, that
gets us back to square one. We thought the reason רבי יהודה
Rabi Yehuda. did not have had only one pedestal and not two
was because was because he couldn't trust you to label them. You'd
get it mixed up and it tries to say that's his concern
about these boxes of money for the- for the כתיבה, kseiva, the
boxes of money for the- for the birds of עולה and the
birds of חטאת.
But the גמרא Gmara says no, that's not based on labeling, there
he trusts labeling. That's a different concern. The concern is the owner
will die, it'll be mixed up, and then it got us into
the whole digression, if the owner dies and it got mixed up,
why not throw the money out? No you can't throw the money
out because he doesn't hold of ברירה. breira. Fine. But that's his
concern there, that the owner will die and there'll be mixed up
money. So but he basically holds of כתיבה, kseiva, so we're back
to question one. Why can't he have two pedestals? So let's take
a look. So- כתיבה? kseiva? Writing, labeling. Labeling. גמרא Gemara says like
this. So גמרא says like this. It says, okay so- אמר רבי
יוחנן Amar Rabi Yochanan okay דהשתא דאמינא de-hashta de-amina now that we
hold of רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda? אין ברירה, ein breira, he doesn't
hold of ברירה breira and that's his concern about the mixed up
money about the guy that dies, כתיבה אית ליה kseiva is leh
but he holds of labeling and normally he holds of these different
boxes where the money goes in the בית המקדש, people will pay
attention to labeling. יום כיפורים נמי נהוי תרי. Yom Kippurim nami nahavi
terei. So I get- I don't get it, so why not have
two pedestals on יום כיפור Yom Kippur back to that issue and
נכתוב עליהו ve-nichtov aleihu and label them? That was our question all
along and now we see that he does hold of labeling. So
the גמרא says משום חולשא דכהן גדול mishum chulsha de-Kohen Gadol
because the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol will be so exhausted, he'll be
so running around, meaning the חולשא chulsha is not just exhausted but
you know so distressed and distracted and overwhelmed and he'll be running
around, לאו אדעתיה, lav adaiteih, he won't be paying attention, like labeling
might work under normal circumstances but not under rushed and distracted and
pressured circumstances. So here the labeling won't work. What is it somebody-
who said at the end of yesterday's שיעור shiur that there was
a t-shirt out that basically says what, you know, if you make
something idiot proof somebody will just build a better idiot? So you
said that Josh? Okay so that's it, okay. So you hold labeling
normally works but not on יום כיפור Yom Kippur when the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol is running around like a madman then labeling won't
work. Okay, so that's why he can't have two different things and
you'll get confused which is which.
he's got all the sins of the Jewish people.
Okay, so דאי לא תימא הכי de-ei lo teima hachi
because if you don't say that, דלא כתיב נמי de-lo ketiv nami
you could have figured it out even without labeling. You forget whether
you've labeled. Michael says make them different colors. Gmara says there's other
ways of telling the difference. Okay, הנא נפיש בזיא hana nafish bazya
the blood of the ox is a lot more than the blood
of a goat. So just look, which has which has more blood?
Which bowl? וכי תימא לא מקבלי כולה ve-chi teima lo mikablei kulei
maybe you'll say you don't catch all of the blood of the
ox, so you won't see the difference in volume. No, ואמר רבי
יהודה השוחט צריך שיקבל כל דמו של פר ve-amar rabi yehuda ha-shochet
tzarich she-yekabel kol damo shel par the shochet in general has to
catch all of the blood, שנאמר she-ne-emar is the verse says: ואת
כל דם הפר ישפוך אל יסוד המזבח, אל יסוד מזבח העולה ve-et
kol dam ha-par yishpoch el yesod ha-mizbe'ach, el yesod mizbach ha-olah all
the blood. So why labeling? Why doesn't he just look, which one
which bowl is the huge bowl? וכי תימא דילמא משתפיך מיניה ve-chi
teima dilma mishtapech minei
and if you say oh maybe some some blood was spilled. Nevertheless,
you would say one bowl will be bigger. But anyway, חחוורא ואסומקא
cha-chivra ve-asumka so what? The blood of of a goat is whiter
and the blood of of of an ox is redder. So there's
a visual difference, so you know, still, he should be able to
look and to tell. אלא משום חולשא דכהן גדול לאו אדעתיה ela
mishum chulsha de-kohen gadol lav adateih no,
because of his weakness, because of his running around, you know, he's
not going to stop to process and think oh wait, wait, wait,
it's you know, it's the big one, it's the redder one. He
won't be discerning and he'll just you know and he'll make a
mistake. So הכי נמי משום חולשא דכהן גדול לאו אדעתיה hachi nami
mishum chulsha de-kohen gadol lav adateih so here too same story why
we didn't label it. So if you have two, you'll forget which
one is which and you'll get confused. If you have one, you
have to pay attention as you're taking one off and putting the
other down, you know exactly what you're doing. Of course, I still
don't get it. If you ask me, anytime I had two in
my hands at the same time, I could say wait a minute,
which was which? But maybe if it's clear right and left, I
don't know, you're in the process, somehow that will make it you'll
get much less confused than if you put them both down and
stepped away, then you'll can really get confused. Okay. Now we have
a practical application. What's a practical application? Practical application is liturgy. Okay,
and this is a fascinating thing because the first time I believe
in all of יומא Yoma we actually get a insight into the
liturgy of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and how all the and how
all the discussions we've been having about the עבודה avodah became part
of that they actually the idea of saying over the עבודה avodah
as part of the liturgy of יום כיפור Yom Kippur. was something
that went back to the time of אמוראים Amoraim and how some
of these issues and debates and discussions will impact what actually we
say when we do the עבודה avodah on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So let's take a look. The גמרא says ההוא דנחית קמיה דרבא
hahu de-nachit kameih de-rava a certain שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur went down
in front of רבא Rava that means led the davening because the
place that you led the davening from was actually like a pit,
right, a pit, a lower than the rest of the floor, because
like calling out to God from the depths. So a person went
down in front of רבא Rava to lead the davening on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. אמר and he said when he described this part
of the עבודה, avodah, יצא והניחו על כן שני yatza ve-hinnicho al
kan sheni the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol came out, put the blood
of the ox on the second pedestal, שבהיכל, she-ba-heichal,
נטל דם הפר והניח דם השעיר. natol dam ha-par ve-hinnniach dam ha-sa'ir.
He took the blood of the ox and he put down the
blood of the goat. So אמר ליה amar lei so רבא Rava
said to the שליח ציבור, shliach tzibbur, חדא כרבנן וחדא כרבי יהודה
chada ke-rabanan ve-chada ke-rabi yehuda you're conflating two opinions. One like the
רבנן Rabanan and one like רבי יהודה. Rabi Yehuda Now which is
how do you know that? The fact that he said there was
a second pedestal, that's the רבנן. Rabanan. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, only
had one pedestal. But then where did he say the order was?
He said first he took the blood of the of the ox
and then he put down the blood of the goat. Now if
you have two pedestals, what do you do? Right? You're done with
the goat. What do you do if you have two pedestals? What's
the first thing you do? You put the blood of the goat
down. Right? Then you go over to the other pedestal and you
take the blood of the ox. So if you have two pedestals,
the first thing you would do would put down the blood of
the goat. If you hold one pedestal, you come out with the
blood of the goat. So you so there's only space presumably on
the pedestal for one for one vessel. So you have to take
the blood of the ox first and then put down the blood
of the goat. So he said two pedestals, which would have meant
put the blood of the goat down first. But then but then
he said take the blood of the ox, which means that there's
only one pedestal. So he says you started off like the רבנן
Rabanan and you ended like רבי יהודה.
So אימא eima so rather say הניח דם השעיר ונטל דם הפר
hinnniach dam ha-sa'ir ve-natol dam ha-par
rather say no, put down the blood of the goat, take the
blood of the ox, which means who's פשט pshat is that? Whose
position is it, the רבנן Rabanan or רבי יהודה? That first you
put down the blood of the goat. Who's paying attention? The רבנן.
Rabanan. Right? So they had two pedestals. If you have one, again,
you have to first make room for it by taking the one
of the ox. And no. So he says we פסק pasken like
the רבנן, Rabanan, so say there are two pedestals, that was good,
כן שני, kan sheni, but then say the order correctly. Put down
the blood of the goat and then take the blood of the
ox. So that is the debate of one or two, where רבי
יהודה's concern is not that generally he doesn't trust labeling, but on
this day with this type of being of pressure and whatnot, there
he's concerned that the labeling will not, that that it won't do
any good, and he wants to have it, you know, foolproof, and
he makes only one pedestal. But in the end רבא Rava said
we rule like the Rabbis with the נפקא מינה nafka mina being
the נוסח nusach of the דאבנינג davening on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur
Let's go now to the next, next quote from the משנה. Okay,
והזה ממנו על הפרוכת כנגד ארון מבחוץ. v'hizah mimenu al haparochet keneged
aron mibachutz.
So now he has, he's got the blood of the, so now
he's done that, he switched the bloods. He did the blood of
the ox on the inside, he went and he שחט shechted the
goat without וידוי viduy I'll remind you, he did the blood of
the goat on the inside, on the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, and
now it says he comes out and he and he does it
on and he sprinkles it on the פרוכת parochet standing outside
the קודש קדשים.
Kodesh Kodashim. Okay. You have some idea, but anyway there you are,
right here is the,
this way?
No, it was this way, okay. So actually it wasn't
an ארון, aron, it was a stone, whatever it was, okay. So
he goes in and first he does the one and the seven
for the פר, par, then he walks out, right, he שחט shechts
the goat, okay, he שחט shechts the goat, he catches the blood,
he walks back in, he does the one and the seven for,
oh I'm sorry I skipped. Okay, he did the פר, par, right,
he went out and he put it on the pedestal, okay. Then
he walked in, he שחט shechted the goat, walked back in, did
the one and the seven for the goat, walked back out, now
let's say it's like the Rabbis,
not like רבי יהודה, so he puts the blood of the goat
down,
so
he put it down on this pedestal, here was already the blood
of the ox which was waiting since last time, now took the
blood of the ox and he stands here by the פרוכת parochet
and now he's going to do one and seven on the פרוכת
parochet standing outside the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
Okay. Somebody's stirring that blood of the פר?
par? No, I think it was a short enough time that you
didn't have to worry about
that. Okay, so that's where we're up to. Okay, did the פר,
par, went out, שחט shechted the goat, did the פר, par, left
the blood of the פר par on a pedestal, went out, שחט
shechted the goat, came back in, did the one and the seven,
came back out, put the blood down on pedestal number two according
to the Rabbis, took the blood of the פר, par, he's standing
outside and now he's going to do
one and seven
on the פרוכת parochet standing outside. Outside, right, outside the קודש קדשים
Kodesh Kodashim in the היכל Heichal and now he's going to do
one and seven.
יום כיפור's Yom Kippur, the only day of the year when this
blood is placed upon the incense golden altar?
Right, correct, even the part that the עבודה avodah is done on
the inside is not on the מזבח הזהב, mizbeach hazahav, correct.
Right, so it's the only day of the year where there's blood
on that altar.
Yes, I believe that is correct. Yep. Okay. So, תנו רבנן, tanu
rabbanan, וכן יעשה, v'chen yaaseh, so now we're going to get to
this idea of where you know that he does it on the
curtain, then we'll worry as דוב Dov was saying on the golden
altar. וכן יעשה לאהל מועד השוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם, v'chen yaaseh l'ohel
moed hashochen itam b'toch tumotam, okay. So the פסוק pasuk says what?
I'll just read to you the context where we are. ושחט את
שעיר החטאת
אשר לעם
והביא
את דמו מבית לפרוכת ועשה את דמו כאשר עשה לדם הפר והזה
אתו על הכפרת ולפני הכפרת.
v'shachat et seir hachatat asher la'am v'hevi et damo mibeit laparochet
v'asah
et damo ka'asher asah l'dam hapar v'hizah oto al hakapporet v'lifne
hakapporet. Remember we learned the אתו oto tells you one, the connection
to the דם הפר dam hapar tells you use the seven, the
על ולפני al v'lifne tell you it doesn't directly hit, it just
goes in front of, fine. וכפר על הקודש מטומאת בני ישראל ומפשעיהם
לכל חטאתם, v'chiper al hakodesh mitumot b'ne yisrael umipishehem l'chol chatotam, so
he's מכפר mechaper for the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. וכן יעשה לאהל
מועד השוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם. v'chen yaaseh l'ohel moed hashochen itam b'toch
tumotam. So what's וכן יעשה לאהל מועד? v'chen yaaseh l'ohel moed? I
mean the whole thing, the היכל Heichal and the קודש קדשים Kodesh
Kodashim are called, you know, are the אהל מועד ohel moed of
the תורה. Torah. So what's the וכן יעשה? v'chen yaaseh? So we
understand the וכן יעשה v'chen yaaseh is the sprinkling that gets done
on the פרוכת parochet over there, which is quite fascinating by the
way that designates all of אהל מועד, ohel moed, the focus on
the פרוכת parochet we'd still assume is a focus on the קודש
קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. But we're translating the verse וכן יעשה, v'chen yaaseh,
so the verse does not explicitly speak about the sprinklings on the
פרוכת, parochet, okay, but we are translating וכן יעשה לאהל מועד, v'chen
yaaseh l'ohel moed, the entire אהל מועד, ohel moed, to mean a
sprinkling that's getting done on the פרוכת. parochet. So let's take a
look. Okay. So מה תלמוד לומר, ma talmud lomar, what is it
teaching you? כשם שמזה לפני ולפנים, keshem shemazzeh lifnai v'lifnim, the same
way he does it on the inside, כך מזה בהיכל. kach mazzeh
b'heichal. So the אהל מועד ohel moed is that you're standing in
the אהל מועד, ohel moed, you're standing in the היכל. Heichal. There's
going to be a sprinkling in the היכל. Heichal. מה לפני ולפנים
אחת למעלה ושבע למטה, mah lifnai v'lifnim achat l'maalah v'sheva l'maatah, by
the same way, and by the way the same way when you
do it inside the וכן v'chen which equates them is the same
way inside it's one above and seven below
מדם הפר, midam hapar, כך מזה בהיכל. kach mazzeh b'heichal. So similarly
when you do it outside, you do one and seven and you
do it with the פר. par. וכשם שלפני ולפנים אחת למעלה ושבע
למטה מדם השעיר, ucheshem she'lifnai v'lifnim achat l'maalah v'sheva l'maatah midam haseir,
the same way on the inside again so the תורה Torah never
says do both the blood of the ox and the blood of
the goat, it just says do the same thing. So do the
same thing. Do the same thing. One and seven with the ox,
one and seven with the goat. כך מזה בהיכל, kach mazeh ba-heichal,
the same by the היכל. heichal. But again, saying that it's on
the פרוכת parochet is not in the פסוקים, psukim, that the וכן
ve-chen tells you fine, one and seven ox, one and seven goat,
but חז"ל's Chazal understanding is לאוהל מועד le-ohel moed means standing in
the היכל heichal and doing it on the פרוכת. parochet. השוכן איתם
בתוך טומאתם, ha-shochen itam be-toch tumatam, right? And now we're having at
the end of the פסוק pasuk says וכן יעשה לאוהל מועד השוכן
איתם ve-chen yaaseh le-ohel moed ha-shochen itam who dwells amongst them בתוך
טומאתם, be-toch tumatam, okay? So אפילו בשעה שהם טמאים שכינה עמהם, afilu
be-shaat she-hem tme'im shechina imahem, even when they are טמא, tamei, right?
God's divine presence continues to be among them. And as I said,
this is like a major point of the whole idea of the
עבודה avoda on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur which is God says that
he, you know, ושכנתי בתוכם, ve-shachanti be-tocham, make me an אוהל מועד
ohel moed ושכנתי בתוכם ve-shachanti be-tocham I'll dwell in your midst. But
the problem is we're human beings, so we sin, and sin creates
טומאה, tuma, and God has to continue to dwell with us even
amongst our טומאה, tuma, השוכן איתם בתוך טומאתם. ha-shochen itam be-toch tumatam.
But for that to continue to happen, once a year we got
to clean out the טומאה, tuma, and we have to make it
more possible, go through this ritual. As I said, this is the
national, right? We all focus on יום כיפור Yom Kippur very much
at the personal level of our own תשובה teshuva and our own
atonement, but the focus of the עבודה avoda on יום כיפור is
at the national level to cleanse, do a cleansing of the sins
at the national level, which allows God to continue to dwell among
the nation and to continue to dwell among the people. And therefore
that's exactly why it's juxtaposed here וכיפר, ve-chiper, right? When it says
וכיפר על הקודש, ve-chiper al ha-kodesh, we're not talking about atoning for
somebody's sins. We're talking about cleansing the sanctuary from the טומאה tuma
that was created by the sin. So it cleanses the sanctuary מטומאות
בני ישראל, mi-tumot b'nei yisrael, right? So it says what's the פסוק?
pasuk? וכיפר
על הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל ומפשעיהם לכל חטאתם. ve-chiper al ha-kodesh mi-tumot
b'nei yisrael u-mi-pisheihem le-chol chatatam. It cleanses and it cleanses the אוהל
מועד ohel moed because God dwells with us in our טומאה, tuma,
but we have to do something about cleaning that טומאה tuma up
on a regular basis to allow that to continue. God will sustain
it but it will only sustain it for so long. And that's
השוכן איתם בתוך טומאתם. ha-shochen itam be-toch tumatam. But we do our
job of cleansing the טומאה tuma once a year. Okay, אפילו בזמן
שהם טמאים שכינה שרויה ביניהם. afilu be-zman she-hem tme'im shechina shruya beineihem.
Now, אמר ליה ההוא צדוקי לרבי חנינא. amar lei hahu tzaduki le-Rabbi
Chanina. So a certain Sadducee said to Rabbi Chanina—I didn't check, it
probably is, it probably originally says ההוא מינא. hahu mina. Does anybody
have some of those new English editions? I think have the improved,
the correct... what do you have there Michael? Is that the Artscroll
גמרא you've got? מינא, mina, right, okay, that's what I thought. So
a certain heretic said to Rabbi Chanina—and a heretic is very often
a Jewish Christian—okay, said to him השתא
ברי טמאים אתון. hashta bari tme'im atun. You are definitely impure nowadays,
meaning you've been rejected. I would re-translate it as: You've been rejected
by God because of your sins. Okay, דכתיב, de-chtiv, טומאתה בשוליה. tumata
be-shuleha. Your, your, your טומאה tuma is on the,
you know, is on the hanging to the hems of your garment,
which is actually very much evoking the whole טומאה tuma of menstruation
and a נידה niddah and gets to other issues about how נידה
niddah becomes a focus, but anyway. He says: You're all sullied and
טמא tamei and God has rejected you. Right? That's some Christian claim,
we've been rejected by God. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to
him תא חזי מה כתיב בהו. ta chazi ma kativ behu. Let
me show you what it says about them: השוכן איתם בתוך טומאתם.
ha-shochen itam be-toch tumatam. We might be טמא tamei but God stays
with us. Okay? So, you think, you know, so אפילו בזמן שהם
טמאים שכינה שרויה ביניהם. afilu be-zman she-hem tme'im shechina shruya beineihem. We
just need that once a year to clean it out though.
Yeah,
but now we're abstracting that. Well, that's anyway, that's for the מקדש.
mikdash. We don't have a מקדש. mikdash. Anyway, that's also like an
interesting point, right? Because it, look, it raises the whole question of
post-מקדש. mikdash. Does that mean God has departed from us? How do
we interpret... right? But Michael is correct. You know, the boldness here
is that it's taking it out of the פשט, pshat, which is
God is שוכן shochen amongst us in the presence of the מקדש,
mikdash, number one. So it's only true when there's a מקדש. mikdash.
And number two, when we go through this ritual. Okay? So without
a מקדש mikdash and without a ritual, you might say the פסוק
pasuk isn't referring to that. But the חז"ל Chazal of course reject
that and say no, השוכן איתם בתוך טומאתם. ha-shochen itam be-toch tumatam.
God is always with us, even without a מקדש, mikdash, in all
times, even if we are טמא. tamei. You know, we have not
been rejected by God. So as opposed to, you know, the claim
of the angry God of the, you know, Old Testament that, you
know, punishes and rejects and so on, this response is: No matter
how טמא tamei we are, God is always, continues to dwell with
us. Okay, so we'll end with that for now.
Yeah, and Rabbi Uzziah also wanted...